Today's דף daf is קע"ב, Kuf Ayin Bet, 172, and we pick
up three lines in the bottom, three lines excuse me, three lines
from the top. אמר ליה רבא בר רב שילא להנהו כתבי שטרי
אקנייתא. Amar lei Rava bar Rav Shila lehanhu katvei shtarei aknyata. So
now we're dealing with the writing of שטרות shtarot and the how
do you write a שטר shtar that's
post-dated, you know, if you're going to give a שובר shover that'll
be open for abuse. So we spoke about post-dating the שובר, shover,
or
writing explicitly in the שטר shtar that it was post-dated, or writing
a blank שובר, shover, and then sometimes if people don't follow those
rules, then you know then
you only have yourself to blame. You know we gave you the
rules to do it so that the possibility to allow for a
post-dated שטר shtar and the writing of a שובר shover in a
way that won't lead to abuse, but yes if you don't follow
those rules you might get cheated. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says with this sort of in this larger in this context.
אמר ליה רבא בר רב שילא להנהו
כתבי שטרי אקנייתא. Amar lei Rava bar Rav Shila lehanhu katvei shtarei
aknyata. So Rava bar Rav Shila said to those that write שטרי
אקנייתא. shtarei aknyata. Now what does שטרי אקנייתא shtarei aknyata mean? So
the רשב"ם Rashbam interprets it to mean that we're not talking about
a שטר הלואה, shtar halva'ah, not a loan document, but a document
of sale, of a sale of land. Okay,
let's go with that for now. Okay, so it's a sale of
land and therefore and it's a case which we're going to presume
is that there's no אחריות achrayus issue. There's no insurance, so there's
no concern of the לקוחות. lakochos. Either it was land given as
a מתנה, matana, okay, or or
you know it was explicitly excluded אחריות, achrayus, or maybe there was
אחריות. achrayus. I'll get back to that in a minute. But it's
a gift, it's a שטר קנין shtar kinyan of land, okay, and
he said to them the following: כי כתביתו שטרי אקנייתא, ki kasvitu
shtarei aknyata, when you write these שטרות, shtarot, these שטרי קנין, shtarei
kinyan, אי ידעיתו יומא דקנו ביה, ei yiditu yoma dekannu bei, כתבו.
kisvu. If you know the day that the קנין kinyan was done,
so the קנין kinyan was done on, you know, on November 1st,
and here you are now it's January 1st. So if you remember
you didn't get around to writing it. Okay, now if you didn't
get around to writing it it means it's not a שטר קנין,
shtar kinyan, meaning it might have been that the person sold land,
but if if the land was sold on November 1st, they didn't
sell it with a שטר, shtar, right? Because so they sold it
maybe with a קנין חליפין, kinyan chalifin, you know, they sold it
with a חזקה, chazakah, maybe they didn't even sell land, maybe he
sold his, you know, his Mercedes. Now you see I've moved on
from the from the, okay, anyway, so and you want and you
want just some proof of that now. Okay, so question is what
good is a שטר shtar going to do with מטלטלין, metaltelin, somebody
can go ahead and whatever. But okay, but let's stick with land.
שטר shtar might only be of a very, very limited use by
מטלטלין. metaltelin. Okay, but anyway, but it's but the קנין kinyan took
place a while ago. They saw it and they're writing the שטר
shtar now a few months later to serve as evidence. How do
they date the שטר? shtar? It's a good question. Do they date
it as of today, January 1st? We the עדים edim saw so
and so sell his land to so and so. Or do they
date it November 1st? Well you should, so that's what he said.
אי ידעיתו יומא דקנו ביה, ei yiditu yoma dekannu bei, if you
know the day that you did the קנין, kinyan, כתבו, kisvu, then
write that in the שטר. shtar. ואי לא, ve'ei lo, and if
you don't know, כתבו יומא דמטו ביה, kisvu yoma dematu bei, write
the day that you're standing in, write today's date, כי היכי דלא
מיתחזי כשיקרא, ki heichi dela mitchazi keshikra, so it should not look
like a lie. Now of course the question we I would always
have is why not write both? You know, today we are signing
the שטר shtar that we saw on such and such a date
so and so for I have no idea, I have no idea
why you don't do both. Okay, but the point is that but
even if you were to do both, the question is what would
you do if you can't remember the date? So should you guess?
Okay,
now you could say let's try to guess. Well they didn't know
obviously you're not allowed to guess. But but you know I could
imagine another scenario. I could imagine saying look, I don't remember exactly
the date. But I know it was before Thanksgiving, okay? Because I
remember after that you know we whatever we did something blah blah
blah and then you know and then the Thanksgiving happened, okay? So
let's just date it as of Thanksgiving, because I know it happened
at least before Thanksgiving. That's a reasonable idea point, right? So actually
that's where he says no, sorry you're not allowed to do it.
מיחזי כשיקרא. meichzi keshikra. You can't put on a date, you know,
that if it's not accurate. Even if you know, now I don't
know what would be if you could write in a שטר, shtar,
it happened on or before Thanksgiving, right? Why don't you write that?
Right? That's always the question. Why not give people a little more
latitude of how to write it? But if all you have available
to you is to write a specific date and you don't know
that specific date, then you have to go with today's date because
that's the only other point that you're certain of. Okay, you're certain
of today's date. So if you know the specific date that it
was sold, write that. If you don't know that specific date, don't
guess, don't say, don't write a date that it must have happened
by this date. No, just write today's date, which really then again
hurts Charlie, poor Charlie, because then it looks like he doesn't own
it, he didn't own it until January 1st. Okay, so that's the
point, which is definitely a חידוש. chiddush. Yes.
What happens in that case? So you know, you wrote it today,
but you did double-sell it because you sold it before to one
person and then to another.
Right, we award it to the person who has the earlier שטר,
shtar, who has the שטר shtar dated that they have it at
the earlier date.
No, but meaning you can still double sell, you're only getting around
to it
today, meanwhile you sold it twice. So both שטר shtar are going
to say January 1st.
Okay, so then whoever, whichever, fine, then they'll have to split it.
Whatever. Yeah. But you'll still reimburse one of them.
Yeah, that's true. Okay, now, so that's in terms of that. Now
I want to say another thing about this שטר קניין shtar kinyan
though, there's more חידושים chiddushim than just the limiting of this because
of מחזי כשקרא. mechzi k'shikra. That's one חידוש. chiddush. Don't say oh
it definitely happened by Thanksgiving, let's just write Thanksgiving. No, if you
don't know specifically write today's date. That's the emphasis of the חידוש.
chiddush. But there's another חידוש chiddush as well because the רשב"ם Rashbam
says not just we're not just dealing with a case of a
שטר shtar that doesn't have אחריות. achrayut. This would even be true
if Michael sold that field to Charlie with אחריות achrayut November 1st.
Now how could I on January 1st sign a document that says
that Charlie bought it on November 1st with אחריות? achrayut? What's going
to be the consequence of this document? It's going to mean that
if it's taken from Charlie, he's going to be able to go
ahead and get reimbursed from Michael, if Michael doesn't have the money
go to the לקוחות. lakuchot. So people who now buy land from
Michael have it, it has liens on it. It's only fair that
they're aware of the liens. Okay? If on November 1st we wrote
that document for Charlie, they would be aware of the liens when
they went to buy land from Michael. But if we wait two
months, write it and date it as of November 1st, which is
accurate, we've given him now liens as of November 1st, but what
about all those poor people that bought land from Michael for the
last two months? Right, they didn't know of the liens. Right? That's
a good question. So the רשב"ם Rashbam points us to another גמרא
Gemara and תוספות Tosafot reinforces this and says here we are not
concerned. We actually think that sales of land are public and well
known, especially when they take place with witnesses, and we assume that
the לקוחות lakuchot are aware that Charlie bought this land even without
a שטר shtar and they know to be on guard you know
and they know when they're buying land from Michael it has liens
on it even before the שטר shtar is written. So when it
deals with sales of land and אחריות, achrayut, not with loans, loans
we say people borrow money in private, they don't want people to
know that I'm hard up for cash. Okay, sales people want to
make public. Charlie wants to let everybody know that he's now got
20 new acres of
land. Okay. So by land even without the שטר shtar even before
the שטר, shtar, the liens exist and we assume people know about
them. And because of that it entitles me two months from now
to pre-date the שטר shtar or to accurately date it but to
write the date two months ago and give him the proof that
he has liens as of November 1st and we are not afraid
the לקוחות lakuchot will be hurt because we assume the לקוחות lakuchot
were aware of it for the last two months.
Yes.
I guess it's just same thing, the assumption is that it's
the assumption is isn't the assumption that that land is transferred they
could always like if I'm the buyer to buy that field
from you and then you borrow then you borrow money from some
other person some third person right okay so then that person wants
to get paid back you don't have the money I've bought a
field from you two months before don't I have isn't the assumption
that I have to know that there could be liens on that
property?
Yeah but that case there wouldn't be liens you bought it before
I borrowed money. Liens only exist after the money is
borrowed and then it's assumed that you know but it's only assumed
that you know because in case of a loan because of a
שטר. shtar. If we did not get around to writing the שטר
shtar for another month, there are no liens until that שטר shtar
is written. By a loan the liens don't exist until the שטר
shtar is written. So if you borrowed money in November and the
עדים eydim didn't get around to writing the document as of December,
they must write December. They are not allowed to write November. If
they write November it's a שטר מוקדם shtar mukdam even though you
borrowed the money in November but because the liens don't exist until
the שטר shtar is written. שטר shtar was written and therefore the
liens are not going to exist until as of today, so when
it's a loan document and they only got around to writing it
later, they absolutely must write today's date.
Even if
they know, to write the original date is to make it a
שטר מוקדם shtar mukdam because in the case of a loan, liens
don't exist until the שטר shtar and therefore by writing an earlier
date, even the accurate date, you are creating liens that don't exist.
So I should A, I don't think I realized, I didn't consciously
that a lien only emerges with legal force through the writing of
the שטר. shtar.
That is what we are finding out now, right, that is
correct.
It's through the loan, but not only through the loan, through the
loan with the writing of the שטר. shtar.
But within these last two lines we've read, did we move from
the שטר shtar that's being written is the deed for the sale
of the land to now the שטר shtar of the loan?
No, we read from the, no, I'm contrasting it to the שטר
shtar of the loan. It's not in the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא
Gemara is talking about a שטר shtar about purchase of land. Right,
so that's what I'm saying, this important conceptual difference. By purchase of
land with אחריות, achrayus, the liens are created through the purchase of
the land and they can be created even without a שטר shtar
because we assume that people know about land sales and the buyers
can be on their be you know protect themselves.
And
therefore when you write the שטר shtar later you can date it
as of the actual date of transaction. By a case of a
loan, liens don't exist until the שטר shtar is written, so if
you don't get around to writing it until later, you cannot write
the original date of the transaction and if you were, it would
be a שטר מוקדם shtar mukdam and would be פסול. pasul. Yes,
Charles?
The issue of land sales are public
knowledge. Both the Roman Empire and the Persian Empire actually had decent
land records, aha, which we have.
Yeah, I know, you've raised that before, why there was no central
repository of records, you know, and why we had to assume that
it's all because of like you know of like like people knowing
other people's business, you know, and like that, you know, it's I
really never understood that. No, definitely assumes a tight-knit community. Okay, אמר
ליה רב לספריה, amar leh Rav le-safreih, so רב Rav said to
his scribe, וכן אמר ליה רב הונא לספריה, ve-khein amar leh Rav
Huna le-safreih, and רב הונא Rav Huna said to his scribe: כי
כתביתו בשילי, ki katbitu bi-Shili,
if you're writing a document in שילי Shili about, you know, you
saw ראובן Reuven borrow a hundred dollars from שמעון Shimon and you're
in שילי Shili when you're writing up the document and let's say
it's the same date even, כי כתביתו בשילי ki katbitu bi-Shili ואף
על גב דמסרו לכון
מילי בהיני, ve-af al gav de-mesiru lakhun mili be-Hini, even though the
words literally were given to you, the testimony was given to you
in מילי, mili, in היני Hini also? In היני, Hini,
okay. Meaning write where, right where you are when you are writing
the testimony, okay. So write: on this and this
date in
היני Hini we testify that ראובן Reuven borrowed a hundred dollars from
שמעון. Shimon. Okay, even so write where you are, not where the
act actually occurred. Now the funny thing is, one minute, but maybe
there's a different ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon in היני Hini than
there is in שילי. Shili. Yeah, when you say פסי בהיני. pasi
be-Hini. Right, so okay, so the רשב"ם Rashbam says, so here the
רשב"ם Rashbam I believe says you write both. One minute, he
says...
yeah, so the רשב"ם Rashbam I'll just read it to you, it's
one, two, three, about eight lines down in the wide lines, he
says: שאתם יושבים שם בשעת כתיבה כגון במקום פלוני כתבנו הכא מה
שראינו במקום פלוני. she-atem yoshevim sham be-sha'at ketivah kigon be-makom ploni katavnu
hakha mah she-rainu be-makom ploni. So here finally he says write both,
which he should always
say. Right, so I don't know why we don't do this by
the date also, okay. Maybe we do do it by the date,
you know, maybe the point before was we always write the name,
the time, the place and the date where you are and the
place and the date where the event occurred. But the חידוש chiddush
before was, if you don't know, right, if you say, meaning for
all I know we do both. We say, you know, on X
date in place Y we testify that on A date in place
B, whatever. Maybe they do have both. So the first חידוש chiddush
of רב Rav was that obviously this is today's date, but what
do you do if again in this document if you don't know
that original date, right? So he says if you know that original
date, going
back to our שטר מכר shtar mekhar document, write it. But if
you don't know that original date, you're going to have to write
today's date, right? Don't say Thanksgiving because you know it occurred after
Thanksgiving, you're going to have to write today's date. So for all
I know they have both lines. רב's Rav question was what do
you write for this fill-in-the-blank? If you know that original date, going
back to our שטר מכר shtar mekhar document, write it. But if
you don't know that original date, you're going to have to write
today's date, right? Don't say Thanksgiving because you know it occurred after
Thanksgiving, you're going to have to write today's date. So for all
I know they have both lines. רב's Rav question was what do
you write for this fill-in-the-blank? If you know... accurately know it and
it's a שטר מכר, Shtar Mecher, not a שטר הלואה, Shtar Halvaah,
write it. If you don't accurately wrote it, fill it in with
today's date. Now what we're talking about is place Y. Okay. So
he says make sure that you write where you are. Now the
רשב"ם Rashbam says you're also going to write where the event took
place, obviously, because you have to know that, right? Because that might
affect some of the particulars, right? And let's say people are going
to get try to bring counterproofs and they're going to say wait,
we were in place B and we didn't see whatever. So you
have to you absolutely have to write where the event took place,
but he says make sure you also write, this is the way
the רשב"ם Rashbam reads it, where you are. Okay. So be clear,
you know, where you are and don't just sort of write that
you were there if you weren't there. That you were writing the
שטר Shtar there if you weren't there. You saw the event take
place there but you're writing the שטר Shtar here. Now that seems
pretty obvious. Like why should you think if you are genuinely writing
both, why, you know, whatever, obviously you should
write, you know, where you are if there's a separate line for
that and then there's a separate line for where the event took
place. One minute. So, so תוספות Tosafot says the חידוש Chiddush is
that היני Hini and שילי Shili are like two little villages that
are right next to each other and everybody is constantly moving between
one and the other.
Okay. מינצא Minsa and פינסקא Pinska are next to each other? They're
not! They're not! No, no, no. It's like I don't know, it's
like Teaneck and Englewood. I'm going to use Teaneck and Englewood. It's
Teaneck and Englewood. Okay. So come on, they're all one big place,
right? Teaneck and Englewood. So don't think that, you know, okay fine,
we're right now in Englewood, but the event took place in Teaneck,
we're just going to say we're in Teaneck. I mean it's two
steps over Teaneck, so we're going to say we're in Teaneck. No.
If you're in Englewood, you write Englewood, you're in Englewood and the
event took place in Teaneck. So that's what תוספות Tosafot says. It
doesn't matter how close these two places are and how much travel
there is between these two places, you write where you are when
you're writing it distinct from where the event took place. Yes.
I think there was one game of Thanksgiving, what's he knows a
week of Thanksgiving, something like that?
I'm not, I'm not going, I'm not going down
that monkey, but I think it's more important to get the date
right.
Well, I don't think this place where you are is מעכב. Me'akev.
I don't think that this, you know, I don't know, you know,
I think that where, oh you know, no, if you just say
ראובן בר שמעון Reuven bar Shimon or you're just saying סתם Stam
they say ראובן בר שמעון Reuven bar Shimon and we're not saying
where, you know. Yeah, I assume that you know which ראובן Reuven
and שמעון Shimon you're talking about that then the the the place
shouldn't be מעכב. Me'akev. You might want to apply to it other
rules about like, you know, when the עדים Eidim say we don't
know, like when you דרישה וחקירה Derishah v'Chakirah the עדים Eidim say
we don't know the place. All right, I understand.
Yeah, the piece of land is only encumbered with liens if there's
אחריות. Achrayut.
Correct. Okay.
Okay. אמר רבא האי מאן דנקיט שטרא בר מאה זוזי. Amar Rava
Hai Man de-Nakit Shtar-a bar Ma'ah Zuzei. Now, now we're going to
get back to issues connected to the idea of the שובר. Shovar.
Somebody has a שטר Shtar of a hundred
זוז. Zuz. Okay. אמר, Amar, now I have a שטר Shtar that
says Michael owes me a hundred זוז. Zuz. אמר שויונהו לי תרי
בני חמשין חמשין. Amar Shavyu-ni-hu li trei benei chamshin chamshin. So I
say to the בית דין, Beis Din, like if Michael were to
pay up fifty, that was our debate before, do I write him
a receipt or do I write myself or do we I get
a new שטר Shtar written as fifty? But he hasn't yet paid
up anything and I just go to the בית דין Beis Din
and I say guys, do me a favor here, I think Michael's
going to pay me up in installments so I want to make
everything easier so just could you just convert my one hundred שטר
Shtar to two fifty שטרות? Shtaros? Okay, that should seem reasonable.
No, I mean you
want to make it two separate שטרות? Shtaros? No, I have one,
could you convert it to two? Right. I mean you want to
make it two separate שטרות? Shtaros? Michael will pay me up fifty,
I'll give him one
and then the other you got me separately.
All right, well let's take a look. Okay, but so what? I'm
losing, I'm giving up my שטר Shtar that says a hundred. Okay,
it's all having the same date, what should be the problem? Okay,
so I'll turn it in, yeah, I'll turn in this שטר Shtar
and in exchange two fifties. לא משוינן להו, Lo Mashvinan Lehu, we
don't do it for him. מאי טעמא, Mai Ta'ama, why why? אמר
רבינא מילתא דניחא ליה למלוה וניחא ליה ללוה Amar Ravina Milsa de-Nicha
lei le-Malveh u-Nicha lei le-Loveh
because this is protecting everybody's interests to not convert a hundred שטר
Shtar into two fifties. Why? ניחא ליה למלוה כדי שיכוף לפורעו. Nicha
lei le-Malveh kedei she-Yikof le-Par'o.
It's good for the מלוה Malveh because if I have a hundred
and you're forced to give you a receipt, we haven't converted it
into a
fifty, then I have leverage to force you to pay up. You
don't want to lose your receipt, I'm holding onto a hundred שטר,
Shtar, so that's going to create extra incentive for you to pay
up
the rest. Okay. וניחא ליה ללוה כי היכי דנשתקם שטריה u-Nicha lei
le-Loveh ki heichi d'Nishtkamm Shtar-ei and it's good for you, here's an
important thing we haven't said yet. It's good for you Michael to
pay up a half a שטר Shtar and have a hundred with
a receipt rather than a fifty. Why is that good? Because there's
a הלכה Halacha which we haven't said yet which is if, if
I come to בית דין Beis Din with a hundred שטר Shtar
and Michael has a receipt that he's paid up fifty, that creates
a suspicion in the court that he might have paid up the
whole thing because we've already seen he's begun to pay. So that's
called a שטר פגום. Shtar Pagum. It is sort of like, you
know, like a cup of wine on קידוש Kiddush is פגום Pagum
if you drink a little. So this שטר Shtar is פגום, Pagum,
a little bit has been taken away from it. Okay. And therefore
I can't collect from Michael even with my שטר Shtar the remaining
fifty until I make a שבועה Shevuah that he hasn't paid up
the
rest. Now who knows I might be... I might not a hundred
percent remember, I might in general be hesitant to make a שבועה.
shvua. So it's a really good position for Michael to be in
to require me to make a שבועה. shvua. Plus I also want
to say it is really bad business to be lending money. You
never make any money out of this deal. You might not get
it paid off, right? You have to take a שבועה shvua to
get it paid off so like you know, I know.
Anyway, so if Michael admits that he still...
No, if he admits I don't have to. But, but
if he doesn't admit then I, even with my שטר, shtar, I
have to take a שבועה. shvua. If he admits I'd have to
double-check that. That'd actually be good, that's a very important question. But,
but yes.
But if I convert a שטר shtar of a hundred into two
שטרות shtarot of fifty. Yeah. And the בית דין Beis Din takes
the שטר shtar of a hundred and tears it or scrapes it
off or whatever they do. So then there's no חשש chashash of
something being פגום. pagum.
Correct. So we, but that's why we're saying we are not going
to convert a hundred into two fifties. Having a hundred actually provides
benefits for the מלווה malveh and the לוה. loveh. The benefit it
provides for the מלווה malveh is is that it scares, it's leverage
for the לוה loveh to pay up the rest because he doesn't
want to lose his receipt and pay a hundred again. And it's
benefits the לוה loveh because it's going to force the מלווה malveh
to make a שבועה shvua with having a hundred with a receipt
as opposed to a fifty. So therefore in this current state of
the hundred, the מלווה malveh and the לוה loveh have both have
different types of benefits from that, and we're not going to change
it to two fifties which are going to make them lose their
particular benefits. One minute, you have to see the next line. Okay.
Oh I see. In other words, it's to the benefit of the
לוה loveh that
it be a hundred שטר shtar with a receipt. He loses on
the fact that he might lose his receipt and he might have
to pay the hundred. But he gains in the fact that the
שטר shtar is פגום pagum and it forces the מלווה... malveh... In
other words, if
I only have a receipt for fifty, but let me the whole
thing, you have a שטר, shtar, you're saying ברי bari I never
got paid. And the שטר shtar says that, that there's a hundred.
I owe you the fifty, why do we
assume because the presence of a receipt makes us make us question
whether it was all... Okay, we're moving on.
Okay so... Okay now. ואמר רבא, V'amar Rava, now but here's the
important חידוש chiddush which is we say the exact same thing in
reverse. Okay? That רבא Rava says, האי מאן דנקיט תרי שטרי דבני
חמישים חמישים. hai man denakit try shtaray debnei chamishin chamishin.
Somebody has two שטרות shtarot of fifty-fifty on the same date. ואמר
שוינהו ניהלי חד בר מאה. v'amar shavinhu nihali chad bar meah. Should
you convert this to me בית דין Beis Din into a one
hundred שטר? shtar? 'Cause I lent him a hundred dollars on this
date, it's just I have two שטרות shtarot of fifty each. Could
you convert it into a hundred? So לא משוינן ליה. lo mashvinan
lei. We don't do that for him. Why? אמר רב אדא בר
מניומי דניחא ליה למלווה וניחא ליה ללווה. amar Rav Adda bar Minyumi
de'nicha lei le'malveh u'nicha lei le'loveh. Having it as two fifties has
particular benefits for the מלווה malveh and the לוה loveh that we're
not going to give up on. What are the particular benefits it
has for the מלווה malveh and the לוה? loveh? ניחא ליה למלווה
כי היכי דלא נפקום שטר. Nicha lei le'malveh ki heichi d'lo nifkum
shtar.
Having two fifties benefits the מלווה malveh 'cause he can give over
the fifty and then he has a fifty שטר shtar that is
not פגום. pagum. Okay. And right, so that benefits him. And it's
ניחא ליה ללווה, nicha lei le'loveh, and it benefits the
לוה... loveh... I lost my place. I lost my place. כי היכי
דלא ניכפיה לפרעיה.
ki heichi
d'lo nikfayei le'pora'ei. That he on, that if he gets a fifty
back and I only have a fifty, he's not afraid he's going
to lose his receipt. So what the גמרא Gemara is saying... No,
it's not backwards. What the גמרא Gemara is saying is that you
know that each one, each scenario has its pluses and its minuses.
Each scenario has particular benefits for the מלווה malveh and bad things
for the מלווה. malveh. Particular benefits for the לוה loveh and bad
things for the לוה. loveh. So since each scenario has its different
mix of benefits and losses for the different parties, we are not
going to just arbitrarily convert one scenario to the next. It might
not be fair to the interested parties. Now the רשב"ם Rashbam says
that's only if both sides don't agree. If both sides do agree,
who are we to stand in their way? Okay, but if the
both sides, if we don't know that both sides agree, we are
not going to change one to the other 'cause each scenario benefits
the מלווה malveh and לוה loveh in different ways. Okay, so that's
a very reasonable and understandable position. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. Okay. דניחא ליה כדי שלא יכפה לפרעיה. de'nicha lei
k'dei she'lo yichpeh le'pora'ei. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, says Rav
Ashi, האי מאן דנקיט שטר בר מאה זוזי. hai man denakit shtar
bar meah zuzei. ואמר שוינהו ניהלי חד בר חמשין. v'amar shavinhu nihali
chad bar chamshin. לא משוינן ליה. Lo mashvinan lei.
So he says look, let's say I'm the מלווה malveh and I
come to בית דין Beis Din and say Charlie owes me a
hundred. And I say guys, listen, poor Charlie there, he's never going
to get the money to pay me up and he feels, you
know, it's going to be so hard. If even if I tell
him I'm מוחל mochel or whatever, it's going to embarrass him. Just
do me this favor, it's a שטר shtar he borrowed from me
a hundred dollars like a, you know, last month, let's just convert
it into a fifty שטר. shtar. Okay? And the עדים, edim, you
know, what's the matter like בכלל מאתיים מנה. bichlal masayim maneh. He
did borrow fifty. Okay, so just write a שטר shtar says he
borrowed fifty. That's not true, that's not false. Right? So why not?
He borrowed a hundred, but we're going to write a שטר. shtar.
We'll tear up the hundred and say he borrowed fifty. So why
not do it? It's nicer for Charlie. No, we don't do it.
לא משוינן ליה. Lo mashvinan lei. We don't do it. מאי טעמא?
Mai ta'ama? Why not? אמרינן האי מפרע פריע. Amrinan hai mipara paria.
Really what happened, we have to be suspicious that what happened is
Charlie paid up the שטר shtar already. And what did Charlie get
after paying the שטר? shtar? He didn't get the שטר, shtar, he...
He got a receipt. Okay, ואמרי ליה, va'amrei lei, and I said
to... ואמר ליה, va'amar lei, and Charlie said, הב לי שטרי, hav
li shtari, give me my שטר, shtar, ואמר ליה, va'amar lei, and
I said to him, אירכס לי. irkas lei. Oh, נבך, nebach, it
was a loss. I lost your שטר. shtar. וכתב ליה תברא, vechataf
lei tavra, I'll write a receipt. Charlie paid up his debt of
a hundred dollars and I gave it to him. And I'm still
holding on to the שטר. shtar. Now what am I going to
do? I'm going to get this שטר shtar of a hundred converted
to a שטר shtar of
fifty. Okay, so וכתב ליה תברא... vechataf lei tavra... and then I
take out the שטר shtar fifty and ואמר ליה... va'amar lei... I'm
sorry, and then I have the שטר shtar fifty and Charlie says,
no, here's my receipt! I say, what are you talking about? That's
a receipt for a hundred-dollar שטר. shtar. האי אחרינא הוא, hai achrina
hu, that's a different loan. This is a fifty-dollar loan, that's not
a hundred-dollar loan. Pay me up the fifty dollars. So we're not
going to do that even though it seems like you're just cutting
Charlie's loan in half, but because of the reality of receipts, okay,
this therefore, if it presents itself as fifty, might be able to
work he against, you know, would work if he had a hundred-dollar,
a receipt for the hundred-dollar loan that he's paid up.
Yes, real life Judge Judy, right?
Okay, moving on. All right. שני אחים, shenei achim, we move on
to the next משנה. Mishna. Now, I must say, the end of
the משנה Mishna gets us back to שטרות, shtarot, which is what
we've been in for a while. I have no idea what the
beginning of the משנה Mishna is doing here, okay? It reminds us
of the fact that there was an earlier section of בבא בתרא.
Bava Batra. שני אחים, shenei achim, it says two brothers, אחד עני
ואחד עשיר, echad ani ve'echad ashir, one poor and one rich. והניחו
להן אביהן מרחץ ובית הבד, vehinnichu lahen avihen merchatz uveit habad, and
he left for them a bathhouse or an olive press. עשוין לשכר,
השכר לאמצע. asuyin lisschar, hasschar la'emtza.
Let's say it was a business, it was made for making money,
so you keep on running it as a business and you divide
the profits. Okay, עשוין לעצמן, asuyin le'atzman, but let's say the father
made it as, you know, made it private, you know, it's a
private bathhouse and an olive press. So הרי ה... harei ha... so
what does the poor person want to do? The poor person says,
let's sell it, right? I can't use it, let's sell it. The
rich person says, I'm not interested in selling. So if you remember
way back in the first פרק, perek, this was a discussion of
גוד או אגוד. gud o agud. If we own something in partnership,
okay, I can tell you either you buy me out or I
buy you out. But here the poor person isn't in a position
to say, I'll buy you out. So he can't force the rich
person to sell. He is stuck with owning this in partnership and
without being able to force the other person to buy him out
or to buy him out, right, or to sell it and divide
the profits, right? He can't force that person. The person says, I
like the way this is right now, you can't force me to
sell this. How about asking him to convert it into a business?
He can't get that either. I don't want a business. I don't
want people running through my property or whatever, right? The status quo
wins. Okay, the only way you can sort of, you know, force
the status quo to change is if you can say either I'll
buy you out or you buy me out. But if you're not
in a position to say that, you go by status quo. So
therefore, הרי העשיר אומר לו, harei ha'ashir omer lo, the rich brother
says to the poor brother, קח לך עבדים וירחצו במרחץ. kach lecha
avadim veyirchatzu bamerchatz.
Look, you're free to use it, you know, you have as much
use of it as I do. Go get your slaves and go
to the bathhouse. You know, you can't do a real bath without
a lot of slaves to attend to you. Oh, נבך, nebach, you
don't have any slaves? That's not my problem. קח לך זיתים ובא
ועשה בבית הבד. kach lecha zeitim uva va'aseh beveit habad. Go take
your olives and use the olive press. Oh, you don't have any
olives? All right, I can't help you, that's not my problem. Okay,
that is the end of that משנה. Mishna. That part is completely
going to be ignored by the גמרא Gemara and I have no
idea what it's doing here at this section of בבא בתרא. Bava
Batra.
Shows that brothers always get along.
Well, to deal, I don't know, but not to remind us that
there was a different part of בבא בתרא. Bava Batra. Now, שנים
שהיו בעיר אחת, שם אחד יוסף בן שמעון. shenayim shehayu be'ir achat,
shem echad Yosef ben Shimon. Back to שטרות. shtarot. Two people in
one city, the name of one is Yosef ben Shimon ושם אחר
יוסף בן שמעון veshem acher Yosef ben Shimon and the other person
is Yosef ben Shimon. They have the exact same names, right? This
is why we do things like Social Security numbers and driver's licenses
and so on because, you know, people's names feel... a lot of
people have the same name, okay? A lot of John Smiths in
the phone book. Okay, אין יכולים להוציא. ein yecholim lehotzi. So what
do you do in that case? If you have a שטר shtar
with the name of Yosef ben Shimon in it, אין יכולים להוציא
שטר חוב זה על זה. ein yecholim lehotzi shtar chov zeh al
zeh. I'm Yosef ben Shimon and I can't go... Well, let's say
I'm Dov Linzer and I can't go to the other Dov Linzer
and say, look, here's a שטר, shtar, you owe me a hundred
dollars. It says Dov Linzer owes Dov Linzer a hundred dollars. Actually,
there's another Dov Linzer, my cousin who lives in... who lives in
Hollywood, Florida. Okay, so look, it says Dov Linzer owes Dov Linzer
a hundred dollars. He says, I don't know you, you owed me,
you paid up the debt and I gave you the שטר shtar
back. Like, who owes who, right? So they can't take a שטר
shtar against one another. ולא אחר יכול להוציא עליהן שטר חוב. velo
acher yachol lehotzi aleihen shtar chov.
Now let's say somebody, Charlie here, comes to me and says, look,
I got a שטר, shtar, it says you, Dov Linzer, owe me
a hundred dollars. I say, what are you talking about? That's my
cousin, that's not me. Okay, so nobody can bring a שטר חוב
shtar chov against them because they can always claim it's the other
guy. Okay, נמצא לאחד בין שטרותיו שטר שיוסף בן שמעון פרוע. nimtza
le'echad bein shtarotav shtar sheYosef ben Shimon parua. Let's say Charlie there
wrote a little note to himself, he dug up, he was going
through his receipts and he got a... like for a year ago,
he wrote a little note to himself, all of Dov Linzer's שטרות
shtarot are paid up. Let's say Charlie there wrote a little note
to himself. He dug up, he was going through his receipts and
he got a, like for a year ago, he wrote a little
note to himself, all of Dov Linzer's שטרות shtarot are paid up.
Okay, so you know what that means? Now he can't collect from
me or from my cousin. Okay, so שטרי שניהם פרועים, shtarei sheneihem
pru'im, and he has to assume that both people's שטרות shtarot are
paid up. Now כיצד יעשו, keitzad ya'asu, so what can we do?
ישלשו. yeshaleshu. So if you want to use, have their name in
a שטר, shtar, go three generations. Okay, don't just do the name
of their father, do the name of their grandfather. ואם
היו משולשים, v'im hayu meshulashim, if their grandfathers had the same names
also, יכתבו סימן, yichtevu siman, write some identifying characteristic. The tall one,
the social security number, the tall one, the short one, the one,
whatever, you know, this, you know, the guy, whatever, so you write
some characteristic. Don't write their clothing, though. Okay, switch that. Okay, and
don't write don't write סימנים simanim that could change. ואם היו מסומנים,
v'im hayu mesumanim,
let's say there were no good distinguishing characteristics, יכתבו כהן. yichtevu kohen.
So write if one of them is a כהן, kohen, which is
first of all like, what is the likelihood that there are no
distinguishing characteristics? But also why are we introducing כהן kohen at this
stage? You would think that that would go way up earlier, like
when we write a שטר, shtar, we always write כהן kohen or
לוי. levi. So you would have even put that before you go
to three generations, right? And that, so that's, and number three, that
doesn't really answer the question and let's say they're both כהנים kohanim
or they're both נפטונים. neftunim. But the point of the משנה mishna
is find something to distinguish them.
Now I think that's a rhetorical phrase, maybe.
But what I think is also interesting is, notice at no point
here did it suggest using mothers' names or grandmothers' names, right? Like
before you start going to סימנים, simanim, even if we're talking about
who's related to who, go up one generation, I mean go up
four generations. But you know, but certainly you could expand it also.
But you know, so that's interesting.
It's just identifying also by the way, yes, because didn't we, there
were so many סוגיות sugyot where the question was we don't know
who the father is. Yes, so the mother is like a more
stable...
right, but just shows you the reality of a patriarchy, that family
identification goes through, you know, fathers. But even if that's true, certainly
once you get to the סימן siman aspect, right, you know, why
can't mother be a סימן? siman? So I had somebody I write
mothers' names in כתובות, ketubot, I mean unless somebody doesn't want me
to, you know, and like I say בן, ben, you know, the
father's name and then I add the mother's. Some people have asked
me to do בן ben the mother and then the father, and
I say no, I'm sorry we're still a patriarchy, okay? The basic
identification is still the father, but then I add also the mother.
So I had some rabbi call me up and he goes, "What's
your הלכה halacha basis for doing this?" I said, "I don't understand
the question. What's the הלכה halacha basis for adding the name of
the משפחה? mishpacha? We say למשפחת l'mishpachat Linzer, you know, למשפחת l'mishpachat
so-and-so." That's never in the גמרא. gemara. The גמרא gemara is always
just the name of the father, but we add it because we
say it's a further identifying characteristic. So the mother's also a further
identifying characteristic, right? I'm not changing the basic, you know, identity by
the father, I'm just adding another identifying characteristic like we add למשפחה.
l'mishpacha. So anyway, so I think, you know, so it's the משנה
mishna never says it, but I think that certainly would be included
in the סימן siman that the משנה mishna here is talking about.
Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says like this: ההוא שטרא hahu
shtar דנפיק לבי דינא d'nafik l'vei dina דרב הונא. d'rav huna.
There was a certain שטר shtar that was presented in front of
the בית דין beit din of רב הונא Rav Huna דהוה כתיב
ביה d'hava ketiv beih אני פלוני בר פלוני ani ploni bar ploni
לויתי ממך מנה. liviti mimcha mana. Oh, this is such a great
thing. Charlie comes to the
בית דין beit din and he has a שטר shtar that says,
"I, Dov Linzer, borrowed a thousand dollars from you." It doesn't say
from Charlie, it says from you. Okay, so Charlie says, "That's me."
So what do we do? Do we assume it means that it
meant Charlie and it was the one that he was the one
that it was written to? Or do maybe I dropped the שטר
shtar and then Charlie found it, you know, or the person who
for whom it was written dropped it and Charlie found it? אמר
רב הונא, amar rav huna, so says רב הונא, Rav Huna, ממך
אפילו ריש גלותא? mimcha afilu resh galuta? I mean there's a question,
רשב"ם rashbam tells us whether you read this with a question mark,
but I'm going to read it with a question mark. I don't
understand. "From you," would that mean even if it was, let's say,
you know, if it was the president of the United States? Well,
actually he wasn't involved in a lot of בית דין beit din
deals, okay. But whatever, even if it was, even if it was
the Queen of England who had a שטר shtar that says "I,
Dov Linzer, borrowed a hundred dollars from you" and the Queen of
England had it, we would think I borrowed a hundred dollars from
the Queen of England? Like, how open are we going to be
to interpreting who the "from you" means, right? Which means that some...
you know, are we always going to assume that "from you" means
the person who is holding on to the שטר? shtar? ואפילו נשבור
מלכא? v'afilu nishvor malka? So ריש גלותא resh galuta was the Jewish
head, you know, נשבור מלכא nishvor malka is a, is the, was
the, you know, the King of Persia or whatever. So meaning how
far... can we really just say "from you" means the person holding
the שטר? shtar? Now I want to pause for a moment and
say that תוספות tosafot makes a very important way of framing the
question. One way of framing the question is that
we know that it means a particular person and can we presume
that the particular person that it is referencing, you know, that he
actually borrowed money from, is the guy that's holding the שטר? shtar?
Or do we have to be concerned... concern that the שטר shtar
was dropped and somebody else found it and it's referring to somebody
else? תוספות Tosafos says there could be another question going on here.
Can this be essentially a bearer bond, like, you know, can it
be a שטר shtar that basically says to pay to the person
who is holding this שטר? shtar? To the person holding this שטר
shtar I owe a thousand dollars. Okay? So it's not really like
it's a real testimony that, you know, that I borrowed from a
particular person. Maybe ממך mimcha is a שטר shtar that is meant
to say the way it functions is by saying whoever is bearing
this שטר shtar is the person to whom I owe a hundred
dollars. So basically I'm like obligating myself to that person whoever happens
to bear that שטר. shtar. Would we, would we, is such a
שטר shtar legitimate? So it's not a question of are we accurately
identifying the right person, but should we interpret the שטר shtar to
mean to whomever is bearing this שטר shtar I owe a hundred
dollars?
So according to that the question is do we recognize the legal
validity of what we're calling a bearer bond?
Right, or do we interpret these words to mean that? Meaning maybe
if it explicitly said I owe to whomever is holding this שטר
shtar a hundred dollars that would be fine, but if it says
I borrowed a hundred dollars from you does it mean a bearer
bond or does it mean from a particular person? And then we
don't know who that particular person was. Okay? So that's like another
possibility of what's going on here. So אמר ליה רב חסדא לרבה,
Amar lei Rav Chisda l'Rabbah, רב
חסדא Rav Chisda said to רבה, Rabbah, פוק עיין בה, puk ayen
bah, go, go try to do some research. דאורתא בעיא לה רב
הונא מינך, D'orta ba'ya lah Rav Huna minach, רב
הונא Rav Huna is like trying to figure out what the הלכה
halacha would be. Tonight he's going to ask you, so go ahead
and do some research today. נפק דק ואשכח, Nafak dak v'ashkach,
he went out, he got onto his computer, he typed it no,
so he went, he investigated and he found out, דתניא, detanya, we
taught a ברייתא, braisa, גט שיש עליו עדים ואין בו זמן, get
sheyesh alav eidim v'ein bo zman, let's say a גט get has
witnesses but it doesn't have time and an undated גט get is
not valid. So אבא שאול אומר, Abba Shaul omer, אבא שאול Abba
Shaul says, אם כתוב בו גרשתיך היום, im katuv bo gerashtich hayom,
if the גט get says I divorced her today, so כשר, kasher,
it's כשר. kasher. אלמא היום ההוא יומא דנפיק ביה משמע, Alma hayom
hahu yoma d'nafik bei mashma, today means the day that it is
being presented. Now along תוספות' Tosafos lines you can say that, well,
let's just say before we get to תוספות. Tosafos. So the normal
פשט pshat would be that, you see that the הלכה halacha of
שטרות shtaros is that even though this thing might mean something else
we interpret it based on the circumstances that present themselves to the
בית דין. beis din. So if a גט get says I divorced
you today and it came in front of בית דין beis din
today, July, what's today? Well, it's the eighteenth of תמוז, Tammuz, that
I know. Okay, today July twelfth and then we will say oh
it's like the שטר shtar says I have divorced you July twelfth
and therefore it's a dated שטר shtar and it's כשר. kasher. So
even though we know that, look, obviously this is a case that
is extreme because obviously the today means something every day you wait
before bringing it to בית דין, beis din, today means the next
day, it's not somebody dropped it and found it or whatever. Today
means something different every single day. Okay? Right? Let's say, you know,
what's the, what's the Orphan Annie song or whatever? I love you
tomorrow, you're always a day away. So today is always today, today
always means a different day the next day. So anyway, so and
nevertheless we will legally interpret it to mean the day that it
is presented in the בית דין beis din and say that it
is a dated גט get and say that it is כשר. kasher.
So it means we're going to bracket our questions of what really
happened and we're going to interpret it based on the meaning it
holds when it's presented to בית דין. beis din. And if that's
true, Charlie comes with a שטר shtar that says I borrowed from
you a hundred dollars. We don't start worrying who I borrowed the
money from. Its legal meaning is the way it's presented to בית
דין beis din and it means that I borrowed it from Charlie.
Okay? So that's a pretty good proof, right? I mean because the
today case is a more extreme case and we're going to say
it's going to be a valid שטר. shtar. All right? So that's
what he says. I'll get back to sort of תוספות' Tosafos read
in a minute. Okay? So he says like this: אלמא היום ההוא
יומא דנפיק ביה משמע, Alma hayom hahu yoma d'nafik bei mashma, it
means the day that it is being presented. So הכא נמי, hacha
nami, ממך, mimcha,
when it says from you, מההוא גברא דנפיק מתותי ידיה משמע, me'hahu
gavra d'nafik mitosei yadei mashma, it means that's going to be the
legal meaning of it even when we're not going to worry that
it was dropped and somebody else. We're going to say it's like
the same way it's like the שטר shtar is giving a date
and has a date in it, this is like this is like
the שטר shtar has Charlie's name in it and it's not and
we don't have to worry about maybe something else happened to it.
So אמר ליה אביי, Amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said back,
דילמא אבא שאול כרבי אליעזר סבירא ליה, dilma Abba Shaul k'Rabbi Eliezer
sevira lei,
no,
maybe the reason it's כשר kasher is not because today makes it
like it's a dated שטר. shtar. It's not a dated גט. get.
So
then why is it כשר? kasher? Because he holds like רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, דאמר עדי מסירה כרתי, d'amar eidi mesira karsi, רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says that you can use the witnesses at the time
that it was handed over who act Actually were physically present and
saw it handed over, to be or not use, they are the
primary witnesses of the גט. get. And therefore, the same way if
a גט get doesn't have signatures, it's good because the witnesses saw
it, if the גט get doesn't have the זמן, zman, it's good
because the witnesses who were there know the date and they supplement
the date. So that's not a dated שטר, shtar, today doesn't make
it a dated שטר. shtar. It's a dated שטר shtar because there
are עדי מסירה, edei mesirah, there were עדי מסירה edei mesirah present.
Now of
course your question should be then why does it say today? Why
was the scenario, why didn't it say a גט get that doesn't
have a זמן zman is כשר kasher because of the עדי מסירה?
edei mesirah? Why did it give a case of a גט get
that says today in it, if today is not needed to make
it a dated גט? get? So תוספות Tosafot says the reason is
it's to balance out any type of תנאי tnai that the person
might have said. Because in גיטין Gittin you might remember we have
a lot of cases that the guy's on his deathbed and he
says here's your גט get if I die, or here's your גט
get when I die, or whatever. And that raises all these questions
of if the guy dies, does it take effect today if I
die, or does it take effect when I die and then it's
too late? So by having the word today in the גט, get,
it's not to make it a dated גט, get, it's to make
it effective as of today and therefore to not to say that
it only took place after the guy died. Which is why by
the way the רשב"ם Rashbam and תוספות Tosafot point out that a
standard גט get says in it מן יומא דנן ולעלם. min yoma
denan u'le'olam. You are divorced from me as of today and in
perpetuity. Okay, but the as of today you would put that even
in a dated שטר, shtar, right? In order to balance out a
תנאי tnai and make it clear that a תנאי tnai doesn't mean
when something happens, no it takes effect as of today if something
is going to happen. But the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer is the today
is not what makes it dated. What makes it dated is the
presence of witnesses. Okay, אבל הכא aval hacha but here ליחוש לנפילה.
leichush linfilah.
We have to be afraid that it was dropped and the guy
I actually borrowed the money from dropped it and Charlie picked it
up, okay? And therefore maybe when it says from you, that does
not sufficient proof that I borrowed it from Charlie and maybe I
don't have to pay Charlie. Now תוספות Tosafot says, so that's within
the line of are we discussing whether the שטר shtar functions as
proof. תוספות, Tosafot, who reads the issue to be about does the
שטר shtar become a bearer bond? No, what I mean is whoever
is holding this שטר shtar I owe a hundred dollars. So that
actually is a good comparison to the case of today. If I
say
I divorce you as of today and the woman comes with her
שטר shtar to בית דין, Beit Din, the as of today means
the שטר shtar took effect today when she presents it to בית
דין. Beit Din. So the same way the today there, meaning it's
dated, not just because maybe I dated her two weeks ago but
I'm going to assume maybe I divorced her two weeks ago but
I assume I divorced her today because today she came to בית
דין. Beit Din. No, it's dated because even if I definitely gave
it to her two weeks ago, the date it takes effect on
is the day she presents it to בית דין Beit Din because
it says the word today. So that's in comparison to if it
says I borrowed from you a hundred dollars, I owe the hundred
dollars to whoever, it doesn't matter who I borrowed the money from,
the effect of the שטר shtar is to make me obligated a
hundred dollars to whoever is holding onto the שטר.
shtar. That's a much better direction to take.
Right, then that's a question of
exactly. So the question is, do we use open-ended terms for תוספות,
Tosafot, not to say that they are becoming that they're testifying in
terms of the way they're presented. Do we use open-ended terms to
mean to say they take
effect in this open-ended way? So when something says today, it takes
effect as of the day it's presented in בית דין. Beit Din.
And when we say I borrowed a hundred dollars from you, the
from you means whoever presents the שטר shtar in בית דין, Beit
Din, that's the from you. Okay, but then the גמרא Gemara rejects
it and it says no, that's maybe not what the today is
doing. Maybe it actually took effect the date it was given
and it's dated because of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and עדי מסירה
כרתי edei mesirah kratei and the whole thing. Okay, so we're still
left with an open question, an open question, we're still left with
the question that when you have an open-ended term of from you,
there are two questions that are in place according to תוספות. Tosafot.
Okay, one question is, does it, is that interpreted to mean it
doesn't matter who I borrowed money from? The whole point of the
שטר shtar is to obligate me to whoever is holding onto it.
That's possibility number one. And possibility number two is, and if you
say that no, I'm only obligated to a very specific concrete person,
can we assume that you are that concrete person, that you're the
one who's holding onto it and it wasn't a different person and
you found it? Okay, so let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes.
אמר
ליה לנפילה לא חיישינן. Amar lei linfilah lo chaishinan.
So רבא Rava said back to אביי, Abaye, no we don't have
to be afraid that it got dropped. Okay, well that's the key
question. ומנא תימא דלא חיישינן לנפילה U'mina teima delo chaishinan linfilah who
told you? How do you know? דתנן. Detnan. שנים שהיו בעיר אחת.
Shnayim shehayu be'ir achas. Here we go, our case. שם אחד יוסף
בן שמעון ושם אחד יוסף בן שמעון. Shem echad Yosef ben Shimon
veshem echad Yosef ben Shimon. אינם יכולים להוציא שטר חוב זה על
זה ולא אחר יכול להוציא עליהם שטר חוב. Einam yecholim lehotzi shtar
chov zeh al zeh velo acher yachol lehotzi aleihem shtar chov. So
two Dov Linzers here, you know, nobody can bring a שטר shtar
against either of us,
okay, because we'll always say it's the other one. ההם על אחרים
יכולים. Hahem al acheirim yecholim.
But if I have a שטר shtar that says Eli owes Dov
Linzer a thousand dollars and I'm holding onto it, I can bring
it to בית דין. Beis Din. Why is that? Why can't Eli
say, no, I owe your cousin the money, you must have dropped
it and you picked it up from him? There's a big difference.
Exactly. Exactly. So there it's a very specific name. So that's exactly
what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. ואמאי? V'amai? Why can
I use that שטר shtar that's written in my name? ליחוש לנפילה?
Leichush lenefila? Why don't we say, oh, maybe it's the other Dov
Linzer? Okay. גמרא Gemara says, אלא לא שמע מינה לנפילה לא חיישינן.
Ella lashma minah lenefila lo chaishinan. You see we're not afraid of
that. You see if you're holding onto the שטר, shtar, we assume
it's referring to you. So there's an obvious difference here. גמרא Gemara
says, ואביי, V'Abaye, אביי Abaye would say back, לנפילה דחד לא חיישינן.
Lenefila dchad lo chaishinan. That one particular person dropped it and one
particular person found it, that we're not afraid. That the exactly this
was written by the other Dov Linzer and he happened to drop
it and you happened to find it, that we're not afraid of.
לנפילה דרבים חיישינן. Lenefila drabim chaishinan.
But the fact that the שטר shtar says from you, it could
have dropped from anybody, anybody who that שטר shtar was written for
dropped it and I found it and I'm presenting it. So that's
a much bigger question. How do we know it was written for
me? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara still has this as an open
question. When it says from you, again I'm reading it with תוספות
Tosfos because I like the possibility, there's two ways in which what
this שטר shtar that Charlie brings from you that he's entitled, that
we could argue he's entitled to the money. Number one, maybe from
you is meant as like a bearer bond and it really it
doesn't matter who I borrowed money from. What I am saying in
this שטר shtar is I will owe a hundred dollars to whoever's
bearing this שטר. shtar. Okay, if that's true, I definitely will owe
Charlie the money. The alternative is, no, it doesn't mean that. It
means I owe a hundred dollars to the person who specifically and
concretely I borrowed the money from. And then the question is, can
we presume that since Charlie is coming with a שטר, shtar, he's
that person and that it's testifying that Charlie is that person? Or
do we have to say, no, the שטר's shtar testimony remains open
ended and even שטר shtar he's holding of it does not mean
it's testifying that he's that person and we have to be afraid
that it might be somebody else. Okay, so let's take a look
at what lets us do a little bit here the next
דף. daf. ועל הא דתניא. V'alahada detanya. Now going back to this
question, can I Dov Linzer take a שטר shtar that says you
know Eli owes Dov Linzer a thousand dollars if there's another Dov
Linzer living in the town? So until now we said of course
you should be able to, like we're not afraid that one the
one Dov Linzer dropped it and the other Dov Linzer found it.
But ועל הא דתניא V'alahada detanya but we taught in a ברייתא:
Beraita: כשם שאין מוציאין שטר חוב זה על זה כך אין מוציאין
על אחרים. Keshem she'ein motzi'in shtar chov zeh al zeh kach ein
motzi'in al acheirim.
But wait, we've got a ברייתא Beraita that says the same way
somebody can't bring a שטר shtar against me because I'll say it's
my cousin who borrowed the money, I can't take a שטר shtar
against somebody else written in my name because they'll say no, no,
no, it was your brother, it was your cousin, it wasn't you.
So what sense does that make, right? How could we be concerned
that that one Dov Linzer dropped it and I found it? Like
that's very hard. Why shouldn't I be able to go ahead and
use a שטר shtar that says Eli borrowed a thousand dollars from
Dov Linzer?
So גמרא Gemara says: במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai kamipalgi? What's that debate about?
What's the logic in that position?
So גמרא Gemara says: באותיות נקנות במסירה קמיפלגי. Be'osiyos niknos bemesirah kamipalgi.
Back to the old case of באותיות נקנות במסירה. osiyos niknos bemesirah.
Is a שטר shtar transferred by the handing over? תנא דידן סבר
אותיות נקנות במסירה. Tanna didan savar osiyos niknos bemesirah.
The transferring over does mean you own it. ותנא ברא סבר אין
אותיות נקנות במסירה. Vetanna bara savar ein osiyos niknos bemesirah. That they
are not. Which basically means that we are afraid that you're not
the Dov Linzer in this שטר. shtar. Okay, we're afraid that either
your cousin dropped it and you found it or your cousin asked
you to hold onto it for him. But if you say אותיות
נקנות במסירה, osiyos niknos bemesirah, then the point is even if this
שטר shtar wasn't written in my name, even if it was written
in my cousin's name, the fact that he's handed that I'm holding
it, you know, if he handed it to me, that would be
the way to transfer the חוב, chov, right? אותיות נקנות במסירה osiyos
niknos bemesirah means it's the way to transfer the חוב. chov. So
let's say that's true. It was written in his name. You're right,
oh maybe it was written in your cousin's name. Fine. Then I'm
claiming that he transferred the חוב chov to me and I'm holding
onto it and I'm still entitled to it. Whereas if you say
אותיות osiyos are not נקנות במסירה, niknos bemesirah, it means that would
not have transferred the debt. And since the handing over to you
would not have transferred the debt, your holding onto us is not
sufficient evidence that it's your שטר. shtar. Maybe it's his שטר shtar
and he dropped it, or maybe it's his שטר shtar and he
had you watch it for him. So basically what the גמרא Gemara
is now shifting to is that we are concerned, the concern for
נפילה דחד nefila dchad or at least for פיקדון דחד. pikadon dchad.
Okay, and so we're going to continue with this discussion tomorrow about
figuring out can I actually use a שטר shtar written in my
name if there's somebody else around who has the same name as
me.
Can't wait. That sounds just implying. But doesn't this imply here that
אותיות נקנות בכתיבה otiot niknot beketiva and the כתיבה? ketiva?